Guide to the James Gutman Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
James Gutman Papers,
1917-1988
Gutmann, James, b. 1897.
ca. 1,750 items (6 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078846
Biographical Note
Professor of philosophy, Columbia University. Gutmann was Director of the University Seminars, 1970-1976. (Columbia University A.B., 1918; A.M., 1919; Ph.D., 1936).
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, memorabilia, photographs, audio cassette, and printed materials. The papers are chiefly professional in nature, concerning teaching, research, students, and some Columbia University academic business, particularly the University Seminars, of which Gutmann was Director from 1970-1976. The files contain letters from colleagues at Columbia and elsewhere. Some of the major correspondents are: Arthur C. Danto, Irwin Edman, Charles Frankel, Horace L. Friess, Sterling P. Lamprecht, John H. Randall, and Herbert Schneider. There are special correspondence files devoted to Joseph Frank (1916-1970), Dean of the Colorado Rocky Mountain School, Fritz Marti, and numerous letters written to Gutmann in 1964 on his receiving the Nicholas Murray Butler Medal for Philosophy. There are also manuscripts by Gutmann on the myth of Prometheus, mystical experience, Nietzsche and the ethical movement. The subject files include material relating to academic freedom, awards, intergration, Gutmann's biography, Israel, and Gutmann's vitae. In addition there are printed materials by Gutmann and by others inscribed to Gutmann.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
Series III: Subject Files
Series IV: Manuscripts
Series V: Printed Materials
Series VI: Oversize
Subjects
Columbia University--Faculty.; Columbia University--Students.; Columbia University.--University Seminars.; Colorado Rocky Mountain School.; Danto, Arthur Coleman, 1924-; Edman, Irwin, 1896-1954.; Frankel, Charles, 1917-; Friess, Horace L. (Horace Leland), 1900-1975.; Lamprecht, Sterling Power, 1890-; Randall, John Herman, 1899-1980.; Schneider, Herbert.; Frank, Joseph, 1916-; Marti, Fritz, 1894-; Philosophy--Study and teaching.; Philosophy--Research.; College teachers.; Philosophers.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-6. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1978 M-78 Gutmann, James Gift
05/18/89 M-89-05-18 Correspondence, manuscripts, memorabilia, photographs, printed materials, etc. Rosenkrantz, Mrs. Barbara Gutmann Gift
Gift of Mr. James Gutmann, 1978, 1981.
Gift of Mrs. Barbara Gutmann Rosencranz, 1988.
Related Material
Collections related by provenance: James Gutmann Micronesian Papers.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Adler, Felix (Box 1)
  - Barzun, Jacques
  - Behrman, Samuel N.
  - Black, Algernon D.
  - Bush, Wendell T.
  - Carey, Robert T.
  - Coss, John Jacob
  - Danto, Arthur C.
  - Deutsch, Babette
  - Dewey, John
  - Dupee, Frederick W.
  - Edman, Irwin
  - Frankel, Charles
  - Frankfurter, Felix
  - Friess, Horace L.
  - Graffman, Gary & Naomi
  - Ginsberg, Allen
  - Hamlin, Talbot F.
  - Highet, Gilbert
  - Hollander, John
  - Kallen, Horace Meyer
  - Keating, Kenneth B.
  - Kohn, Robert David
  - Lamont, Corliss
  - Loveman, Amy
  - Lamprecht, John Herman
  - Randall, Mercedes
  - Sarton, May
  - Schneider, Herbert W.
  - Tannenbaum, Frank
  - Trilling, Lionel
  - Van Doren, Mark
  - Woodbridge, Frederick J. E.
  - Wouk, Herman
- Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
  - Subseries II.1: Chrolological Correspondence
    - Arranged chronologically by decade, 1934-1960 (Box 2)
    - Arranged chronologically by decade, 1970-1980; 1981 - 1988 (Box 3)
  - Subseries II.2: Special Correspondence Files
    - Butler Medal for Philosophy (letters of congratulations), 1964 (Box 3)
    - Colorado Rocky Mountain School Joseph Frank, Dean, with related correspondence, 1964 - 1970 (Box 3)
    - Marti, Fritz Letters, 1937 - 1972 (Box 3)
    - "Special Correspondence", 1963 - 1977 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 3)
- Series III: Subject Files
  - Americal Civil Liberties Committee Academic freedom (Box 4)
  - Awards (Box 4)
  - "Der Bibliothekar" (Box 4)
  - Biographical file (Box 4)
  - Integrity and integration (Box 4)
  - Israel visits and talk (Box 4)
  - Photographs (Box 4)
  - Vitae (Box 4)
- Series IV: Manuscripts
  - Manuscripts (Box 5)
- Series V: Printed Materials
  - Articles by Gutmann and others inscribed to him (Box 6)
- Series VI: Oversize
  - "Association of the Degallbladderized" (Box 270)